Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
The U.S. Department of Education
We ended last time talking about
the narrative conception of the self.
We were testing the narrative conception
of the self and the idea
of obligations of solidarity or membership
that did not flow from consent
that claimed us for reasons unrelated
to a contract or an agreement
or a choice we may have made.
And we were debating among ourselves whether
there are any obligations of this kind
or whether all apparent
obligations of solidarity and membership
can be translated into consent or reciprocity
or a universal duty that we owe persons qua persons.
And then there were those who defended
the idea of loyalty and of patriotism.
So the idea of loyalty
and of solidarity and of membership
gathered a certain kind of
intuitive moral force in our discussion.
And then, as we concluded,
we considered what seems to be
a pretty powerful counter-example to that idea.
Namely, the film of those
southern segregationists in the 1950s.
And they talked all about their traditions, their history,
the way in which their identities
were bound up with their life history.
Do you remember that?
And what flowed from that history,
from that narrative sense of
identity for those southern segregationists?
They said we have to defend our way of life.
Is this a fatal or
a decisive objection to the idea
of the narrative conception of the self?
That's the question we were left with.
What I would like to do today
is to advance an argument and
see what you make of it.
And let me tell you what that argument is.
I would like to defend
the narrative conception of the person
as against the voluntrous conception.
I would like to defend
the idea that there are
obligations of solidarity or membership.
Then, I want to suggest
that there being such obligations,
lends force to the idea,
when we turn to justice,
that arguments about justice
can't be detached, cannot be detached after all,
from questions of the good.
But I wanted to distinguish two different ways
in which justice might be tied to the good
and argue for one of them.
Now, the voluntrous conception of
the person of Kant and Rawls,
we saw was powerful and liberating.
A further appeal is its universal aspiration.
The idea of treating persons as persons,
without prejudice, without discrimination.
And I think that's what led some among us
to argue that, okay, maybe
there are obligations of membership,
but they are always subordinate,
they must always be subordinate.
To the duties that we
have to human beings as such,
the universal duties.
But is that right?
If our encompassing loyalties should always take precedence
over more particular ones,
then the distinction between friends and strangers
should ideally be overcome.
Our special concern for the welfare of friends
would be a kind of prejudice.
A measure of our distance from universal human concern.
But if you look closely at that idea,
what kind of a moral universe,
what kind of moral imagination would that lead you to?
The enlightenment philosopher Montesquieu
gives perhaps the most powerful,
and I think ultimately the most honest account
of where this relentless,
universalizing tendency
leads the moral imagination.
Here's how Montesquieu put it.
He said,
a truly virtuous man
would come to the aid of the most distant stranger
as quickly as to his own friend.
And then he adds,
listen to this,
if men were perfectly virtuous,
they wouldn't have friends.
But it's difficult to imagine a world
in which persons were so virtuous
that they had no friends,
only a universal disposition to friendliness.
The problem isn't simply
that such a world would be difficult to bring about,
that it's unrealistic.
The deeper problem is that
such a world would be difficult to recognize
as a human world.
The love of humanity is a noble secret,
and it's not just a sentimental sentiment.
But most of the time,
we live our lives by smaller solidarities.
This may reflect certain limits
to the bounds of moral sympathy,
but more important,
it reflects the fact
that we learn to love humanity,
not in general,
but through its particular expressions.
So, these are some considerations.
They're not knock-down arguments.
But moral philosophy
can't offer knock-down arguments,
but considerations
of the kinds that we've been discussing
and arguing about all along.
Well, suppose that's right.
One way of assessing whether this picture
of the person and of obligation is right
is to see what are its consequences for justice.
And here's where it confronts a serious problem.
And here we go back to our Southern segment,
back to our Southern segregationists.
They felt the weight of history.
Do we admire their character,
these segregationists,
who wanted to preserve their way of life?
Are we committed to saying,
if we accept the idea of solidarity and membership,
are we committed to saying
that justice is tied to the good
in the sense that justice means
whatever a particular community or tradition
says it means,
including those Southern segregationists?
Here it's important to distinguish
two different ways
in which justice can be tied to the good.
One is a relativist way.
That's the way that says
to think about rights,
to think about justice,
look to the values that happen to prevail
in any given community
at any given time.
Don't judge them by some outside standard,
but instead conceive justice
as a matter of being faithful
to the shared understandings
of a particular tradition.
But there's a problem with this way
of tying justice to the good.
The problem is that it makes justice
wholly conventional,
a product of circumstance.
And this deprives justice
of its critical character.
But there is a second way
in which justice can be tied with
or bound up with the good.
On this second non-relativist way
of linking justice with conceptions of the good,
principles of justice depend
for their justification
not on the values that happen to prevail
at any given moment in a certain place,
but instead on the moral worth
or the intrinsic value
of the ends rights serve.
On this non-relativist view,
the case for recognizing a right
depends on showing that it honors
or advances some important human good.
This second way of tying justice
to the good is not,
strictly speaking,
communitarian,
if by communitarian you mean
just giving over to a particular
individual or a particular group
of people.
It's a way of tying justice
to the good,
or to a particular community,
the definition of justice.
Now what I would like to suggest
that of these two different ways
of linking justice to the good,
the first is insufficient.
Because the first leaves justice
the creature of convention.
It doesn't give us enough moral resources
to respond to those southern segregationists
who invoke their way of life,
their traditions,
their way of doing things.
But if justice is bound up
with the good in a non-relativist way,
there's a big challenge,
a big question to answer.
How can we reason about the good?
What about the fact that people
hold different conceptions of the good,
different ideas about the purposes
of key social institutions?
Different ideas about what social goods
and human goods are worthy of honor
and recognition?
We live in a pluralist society.
People disagree about the good.
That's one of the incentives
to try to find principles of justice
and rights that don't depend
on any particular ends or purposes
or goods.
So is there a way to reason about the good?
Before addressing that question,
I want to address a slightly easier question.
Is it necessary, is it unavoidable
when arguing about justice
to argue about the good?
And my answer to that question is yes.
It's unavoidable.
It's necessary.
So for the remainder of today,
I want to take up,
I want to try to advance that claim.
That reasoning about the good,
about purposes and ends
is inevitable.
And that reasoning about the good
and ends is an unavoidable feature
of arguing about justice.
It's necessary.
Let me see if I can establish that.
And for that, I'd like for us
to begin a discussion of same-sex marriage.
Now, same-sex marriage draws on,
implicates deeply contested
and controversial ideas
religiously.
And so there's a powerful incentive
to embrace a conception of justice
or of rights
that doesn't require the society as a whole
to pass judgment, one way or another,
on those hotly contested
moral and religious questions
about the moral permissibility of homosexuality,
about the proper ends of marriage
as a social institution.
So clearly, if there's an incentive
to resolve this question,
to define people's rights
in a way that doesn't require
the society as a whole
to sort out those moral and religious disputes,
that would be very attractive.
So what I would like to do now
is to see, using the same-sex marriage case,
whether it's possible
to detach one's views
about the moral permissibility of homosexuality
and about the purpose,
the end of marriage,
to detach those questions
from the question of whether the state
should recognize same-sex marriage or not.
So let's begin.
I would like to begin
by hearing the arguments of those
who believe that there should be
no same-sex marriage,
but that the state should only recognize
marriage between a man and a woman.
Do I have volunteers?
I had two.
There were two people I had
and I asked people who had voiced their views already
on the Justice blog,
Mark Luff and Ryan McCaffrey.
Where are you?
Okay.
Mark?
And where's Ryan?
All right.
Let's go first to Mark.
I have sort of a teleological understanding
of the purpose of sex
and the purpose of marriage.
And I think that for people like myself
who are a Christian
and also a Catholic,
the purpose of sex is,
one, for its procreative uses
and two, for a unifying purpose
between a man and a woman
within the institution of marriage.
You have a certain conception
of the purpose or the telos
of human sexuality,
which is bound up with procreation
as well as union.
And the essence of marriage,
the purpose of marriage,
as a social institution,
is to give expression to that telos
and to honor that purpose,
namely the procreative purpose of marriage.
Is that a fair summary of your view?
Yeah.
Where is Ryan?
Go ahead.
Do you agree more or less with Mark's reasons?
Yes, I agree.
I think that the ideal of marriage
involves procreation.
And it's fine that, you know,
homosexuals would go off
and cohabitate with each other,
but the government doesn't have a responsibility
to encourage that.
All right.
So the government should not encourage
homosexual behavior
by conferring the recognition of marriage.
Yeah.
It would be wrong to outlaw it,
but encouraging it is not necessary.
Who has a reply?
Yes.
Hannah.
I'd just like to ask a question to Mark.
Let's say you got married to a woman,
you did not have sex with her before marriage,
and then when you became married,
it became evident that you were an infertile couple.
Do you think that it should be illegal
for you to engage in sex
if children will not result from that act?
Yeah, I think that it is moral,
and that's why I gave the twofold purpose.
So, like, a woman, say,
I think older couples can get married,
a woman who's beyond...
who's already had menopause
and who can't have a child,
because I think that sex has these...
it has purposes beyond procreation.
I hate to be uncouth,
but have you ever engaged in masturbation?
No.
Yeah.
You don't...
You don't have to answer that.
You can...
Well, yeah, I think...
All right.
Just a minute.
No.
Make your...
Make your argument.
No, I'd like to respond to that.
No, I think...
Wait.
Look, we've...
We've done pretty well
over a whole semester,
and we're doing pretty well now,
dealing with questions
that most people think
can't even be discussed
in a university setting.
And, Hannah, you've got...
You have a powerful point.
Make that point
as a general argument
rather than...
Rather than...
Okay.
...as a general argument
rather than...
Okay.
...as a general argument
rather than...
Okay.
...rather than...
...rather than as an interrogative.
Okay.
But make the point.
What's the...
What's the principle
that you're appealing?
Okay.
What's the argument
you have in mind?
All right.
Well, biblically...
Put it in the third person...
Yeah.
Okay.
...rather than...
...rather than in the second person.
Okay.
Sure.
Make...
Make the argument.
Go ahead.
Okay.
Biblically, masturbation
or onanism
is not permissible
because it's, you know,
there's something wrong with sex
if it doesn't produce children
or reinforce the marriage bond.
Right.
But then how can you say
that there's something wrong
that, you know,
masturbation is permissible
if masturbation obviously
is not going to, you know,
create a child?
Yeah.
I think marriage
is society's way
to create this separate institution
where they say,
this is what we hold as a virtue.
Yes, every day we fall short
and people fall short
in so many different other ways.
But I think
that's the way
that we're supposed to be.
And I think
that's the way
that we're supposed to be.
And I think
that's the way
that we're supposed to be.
But I think
that if you personally fall short
in some moral sphere as we all do,
that doesn't take the right
of you to argue.
Alright.
I want you,
you to stay there.
I want to bring in
some other voices
and we'll continue.
Stay there if you would.
Okay.
Go ahead.
I think
that the response
to the masturbate...
Tell us your...
My name's Steve.
Steve.
The response
to the masturbation is,
it's not something
that's permissible.
I don't think anyone
that homosexual sex is impermissible.
It's just that society has no
place in letting you marry yourself
if masturbation is something that you do.
Well, alright, Hannah.
Alright, Steve has drawn...
Alright, that's a good argument.
Steve has drawn our attention to the
fact that there are two issues here.
One of them is the
moral permissibility of various practices.
The other is the fit between certain practices,
whatever their moral permissibility,
with the honor or recognition that
the state should accord in allowing marriage.
So Steve has a pretty good counterargument.
What do you say to Steve?
Well, I think that it's clear
that human sexuality is something that is,
you know, inherent in, I believe, most people.
And it's not something you can avoid.
And masturbation, I mean, yeah, you can,
you can't marry yourself,
but I don't think that
takes away from the fact that,
you know, homosexuals are people too.
And I just, I can't understand why
they wouldn't be able to marry each other.
If you want to marry yourself,
I mean, I don't know
if you can legally do that.
That's fine, but I don't think that...
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Now here we're deciding,
here we're deliberating as if
legislators what the law should be.
So you said, Steve, that's fine.
Does that mean as a legislator you
would vote for a law of marriage
that would be so broad that
it would let people marry themselves?
Well, I mean, that's really beyond the pale of, like,
anything that would really happen, but I don't think that...
But in principle.
Yeah, in principle.
Yes?
Yeah, sure, I mean, if Steve wants to marry himself,
I'm not going to stop him.
I think that there's...
And you would confer state
recognition on that solo marriage?
Sure.
And while we're at it,
what about consensual polygamous marriages?
I actually think that if
the male and the female are...
If the wives and the man and
the husband or the husbands and the wife
are consenting, it should be permissible.
Who else?
I know there are a lot of people who...
Yes, okay, down here.
Stand up and tell us your name.
Victoria.
So we're talking about the
theological reasoning here for marriage,
and I think that's a really good question.
I think that's a really good question.
But I think the problem is that
we're talking about it within the Catholic viewpoint,
whereas the theological and the point to
marriage for another religion or someone who's
an atheist could be completely different, and
the government doesn't have a right to
impose the theological reasoning for Catholicism on
everyone in the state, which is what my
problem is with not allowing same-sex marriage.
Because I mean, your beliefs
are your beliefs, and that's fine.
but civil union is not marriage within the Catholic Church.
And the state has a right to
recognize a civil union between whoever it wants,
but does not have a right to impose the beliefs
of a certain minority or majority or whoever it is,
based on a religion within our state.
All right, Victoria, good. A question.
Do you think the state should recognize same-sex marriage
or just same-sex civil unions as something short of marriage?
Well, I think that the state doesn't have a
right to recognize it as marriage within a church,
because that is not their place.
But whereas civil union, I see civil union as
essentially the same thing, except not under a religion.
And the state has a
right to recognize a civil union.
All right.
So Victoria's argument is that the state should
recognize a civil union as something short of marriage,
but the state's argument is that the state should not try
to decide the question of what the telos of marriage is.
That's only something that religious communities can decide.
Who else?
My point is I don't see why we
feel like state should recognize marriages at all.
So I'm like one of these 70 people
who voted state should not recognize any marriages,
because I believe it is a union between a
male and a female or two males or two females.
But there is no reason to ask state
to give permission to me to unite myself.
And some might say that if state
recognizes these marriages, it will help children.
It will have a binding effect.
But in reality, I don't think
it actually has a binding effect.
All right. Tell us your name.
Cezanne.
So Victoria and Cezanne's comment is that, you know,
we have a lot of problems with our marriage.
We have a lot of problems with our marriage.
Victoria and Cezanne's comments differ
from earlier parts of the conversation.
They say the state shouldn't be in the business of honoring or recognizing
or affirming any particular telos or purpose of marriage or of human sexuality.
And Cezanne is among those who says, therefore, maybe the state
should get out of the business of recognizing marriage at all.
Here's the question.
Unless you adopt Cezanne's position, no state recognition of any kind of marriage, is it possible to choose between, to decide
the question of same-sex marriage without taking a stand on the moral and religious controversy over the proper telos of marriage?
Thank you very much to
all of you who have participated.
We'll pick this up next time.
You did a great job.
Thank you.
When we first came together some 13 weeks ago, I tried to warn you that once the
familiar turns strange, once we begin to reflect on our circumstance, it's never quite the same again.
I hope you have by now experienced
at least a little of this unease.
Because this is the
tension that animates critical reflection.
And political improvement.
And maybe even the moral life as well.
We have two remaining questions to answer.
First, is it necessary, is it unavoidable to take
up questions of the good life and thinking about justice?
Yes.
And is it possible to reason about justice?
Yes, I think so.
Let me try to develop
those answers to those two questions.
Now, as a way of addressing those questions, we
began last time to discuss the question of same-sex marriage.
And we heard from those
who argued against same-sex marriage.
On the grounds that the purpose or telos of marriage, the
purpose of same-sex marriage, is to be a form of self-denial.
And we heard from those
who argued against same-sex marriage.
On the grounds that the purpose or telos
of marriage, is at least in part, procreation.
The bearing and raising of children.
And then there were those who defended same-sex marriage.
And they contested that account of
the purpose or telos of marriage.
Arguing.
We don't require, as a condition of heterosexual
marriage, that couples be able or willing to procreate.
We allow infertile couples to marry.
This is Hannah's point in the exchange with Mark.
But then there was another position.
Expressed at the end of our discussion by Victoria.
Who argued, we shouldn't try to decide this question.
We shouldn't, at least at the level
of the state, at the level of law,
try to come to any agreement
on those questions about the good.
Because we live in a pluralist society
where people have different moral and religious convictions.
And so we should try to make law,
and the framework of rights,
neutral with respect to these
competing moral and religious views.
Now it's interesting that others,
some others,
who favor the idea of neutrality,
argued not in favor of restricting
marriage to a man and a woman.
Nor in favor of permitting same-sex marriage.
They argued,
in the name of neutrality,
for a third possibility.
Which is that government
get out of the business
of recognizing any kind of marriage.
That was the third possibility.
Now,
Andrea Mayrose
had an interesting contribution to this debate.
She had a rejoinder
to people who argue for neutrality.
Where is Andrea?
All right.
Andrea, would you be willing,
share with us the view,
if we can get you a microphone.
Share with us your view.
Why do you think that
it's a mistake
for the state to try to be neutral
on moral and even
religious questions like same-sex marriage?
I don't know that it is possible because people's lives
are completely embedded in how they view the world.
And maybe I just agree with Aristotle
that the role of the government
is helping people live in a sort of,
like having a collective understanding
of what is wrong and what is right.
Is it possible,
and one could ask the same question of abortion
that we've been asking of same-sex marriage.
Do you think it's possible
to decide whether abortion should be
permitted or prohibited
without taking into account
or without taking a stand
or making a judgment
about the moral permissibility of abortion?
No, I don't think it is.
And I think that's why it's such a controversy
because people are so deeply committed to
like their fundamental beliefs about
whether a fetus is a life or if it isn't.
So, if I believe that like a fetus
is a living being
and has rights
and has like fundamentally the right to live,
then it's very hard for me to say,
but I can put that aside
and let you do what you want.
Because that's like me saying,
well, despite my beliefs,
I'm going to let you commit
what to me is murder.
So, I mean, that's just,
that's just one.
All right, and the analogy
in the same-sex marriage case is
you said you're a defender of same-sex marriage.
Yes.
But you only came to that view
once you were persuaded
on the underlying moral question.
Right. Well, I think particularly in the US,
so many people's beliefs are driven
by their religious beliefs.
And like Mark the other day,
I'm Christian, I'm Catholic,
and I had to decide for myself
like on a lot of thought,
a lot of prayer,
a lot of conversations with other people
that I disagreed with the Catholic standpoint
that homosexuality itself isn't a sin.
And once I came to that sort of conclusion
in my personal relationship with God,
like, I mean, that sounds hokey, right?
That's like, oh, religious.
But a lot of people are religious
and that's where they draw their beliefs
and their views from.
That's when I could say,
yeah, I'm down with the state saying,
go same-sex marriage because I'm okay with that.
And I think that's morally okay.
Good. Thank you.
Now, who would like to reply,
if you can perhaps hang on there for a moment,
who would like to reply to Andrea's idea
that in order to decide the question
of same-sex marriage,
it's necessary to sort out the question
about the moral status of homosexuality
and figuring out the purpose, the telos,
the proper end of marriage.
Who disagrees with Andrea on that point?
Yes.
Well, I think you absolutely can separate
your moral opinion
and what you think the law should be.
For example, I think abortion
is unequivocally morally wrong,
but I do not believe that illegalizing abortion
makes it go away.
I don't believe illegalizing abortion stops it,
and therefore I am pro-choice,
and I do believe the woman should have the choice
as it gives them more safety,
just as maybe morally,
I don't want to get married to a man,
but I'm not going to try to, you know,
impede someone else's freedom
to do what they wish to do
in terms of the law.
Andrea?
Whether the law makes something legal or illegal,
it's implicitly approving or disapproving something.
So if you say, like, by making abortion legal,
we're saying it's okay.
As a society, collectively, we're saying
it's okay with us in our society
to abort a fetus.
If we make it legal, if we make it illegal,
then we're saying collectively as a society,
it's not okay.
And that's why societies have different beliefs.
Tell us your name.
My name is Daniel.
Daniel, what do you say?
Are we saying collectively that it's okay?
Are we saying that collectively we don't want women
who are going to have an abortion anyway
to go to clinics in the side alleys
and have, you know, unsafe conditions?
All right, bring it to the same-sex marriage case.
Why don't you have to decide that which position
you're in favor of same-sex marriage, Daniel,
being legally permitted?
I think it absolutely should be legally permitted
because it's not something telling
me that I need to have,
I need to marry a man.
I absolutely don't, I don't see,
if two men are consenting
adults and want to get married,
I don't see how I could even object to that.
All right.
There's no harm.
There's no harm done either way,
even if it is morally wrong according to me.
All right.
Let me turn to the way the Massachusetts court
who made this landmark ruling in the same-sex marriage case
grappled with the very issue that Andrea and Dan
have been discussing here.
Thanks to both of you very much.
What did the courts say?
This was in the Goodridge case
which required the state of Massachusetts
to extend marriage to same-sex couples.
The court started out, well, the court was conflicted.
If you read that opinion carefully,
the court was conflicted as between the two positions
we've just been hearing,
defended by Andrea and by Dan.
The court begins,
and this is Chief Justice Margaret Marshall's opinion,
it begins with an attempt
at liberal neutrality.
Many people hold deep-seated religious,
moral, and ethical convictions
that marriage should be limited to the union
of one man and one woman
and that homosexual conduct is immoral.
Many hold equally strong religious, moral,
and ethical convictions
that same-sex couples are entitled to be married,
that homosexual persons should be treated no differently
than their heterosexual neighbors.
This is the court.
Neither view answers the question before us.
What is at stake is, quote,
respect for individual autonomy
and equality under law.
At stake is an individual freely choosing
the person with whom to share an exclusive commitment.
In other words, at issue is not
the moral worth of the choice
but the right of the individual to make it.
So this is the liberal neutral strand
in the court opinion,
the voluntrous strand,
the one that emphasizes autonomy, choice, consent.
But the court seemed to realize
that the liberal case, the neutral case,
for recognizing same-sex marriage
doesn't succeed,
doesn't get you all the way to that position
because if it were only a matter
of respect for individual autonomy,
if government were truly neutral
on the moral worth
of voluntary intimate relationships,
then it should adopt a different policy,
which is to remove government
and the state altogether
from according recognition
to certain associations,
certain kinds of unions,
rather than others.
If government really must be neutral,
then the consistent position,
is what we here have been describing
as the third position,
the one defended in the article
by Michael Kinsley,
who argues for the abolition of marriage
at least as a state function.
Perhaps a better term for this
is the disestablishment of religion.
This is Kinsley's proposal.
He points out that the reason
for the opposition to same-sex marriage
is that it would go beyond
neutral toleration
and give same-sex marriage
a government stamp of approval.
That's at the heart of the dispute.
In Aristotle's terms,
at issue here is the proper distribution
of offices and honors,
a matter of social recognition.
Same-sex marriage can't be justified
on the basis of liberal neutrality
or nondiscrimination
or autonomy rights alone,
because the question at stake
in the public debate
is whether same-sex unions
have moral worth,
whether they're worthy of honor
and recognition,
and whether they fit the purpose
of the social institution of marriage.
So, Kinsley says,
you want to be neutral?
Then let churches
and other religious institutions
offer marriage ceremonies.
Let department stores and casinos
get into the act if they want to.
This is Kinsley.
Let couples celebrate their union
in any way they choose
and consider themselves married
whenever they want.
And if three people want to get married,
or if one person wants to marry
himself or herself,
and someone else wants to conduct
a ceremony for them
and declare them married,
let them.
If you and your government
are implicated,
why do you care?
This is Kinsley.
But this is not the position
that the Supreme Judicial Court
of Massachusetts wanted.
They didn't call for the abolition
or for the disestablishment of marriage.
The court did not question
government's role in conferring
social recognition
on some intimate associations
rather than others.
To the contrary,
the court waxes eloquent
about marriage as, quote,
one of our community's most rewarding
and cherished institutions.
And then it goes on
to expand the definition of marriage
to include partners of the same sex.
And in doing so,
it acknowledges that marriage
is more than a matter
of tolerating choices
that individuals make.
It's also a matter
of social recognition and honor.
As Justice Marshall wrote,
in a real sense,
there are three partners
to every civil marriage,
two willing spouses,
and an approving state.
Marriage is at once
a deeply personal commitment,
but also a highly public celebration
of the ideals of mutuality,
companionship, intimacy, fidelity, and family.
This is the court.
Now, this is reaching well beyond
liberal neutrality.
This is celebrating and affirming
marriage as an honorific,
as a form of public recognition.
And therefore, the court found
that it couldn't avoid the debate
about the telos of marriage.
Justice Marshall's opinion
considers and rejects the notion
that the primary purpose of marriage
is procreation.
She points out that there's no requirement
that applicants for a marriage license
who are heterosexuals attest to their ability
or their intention to conceive children.
Fertility is not a condition of marriage.
People who cannot stir from their deathbed,
may marry.
So she advances all kinds of arguments
along the lines that we began last time
about what the proper and the essential nature
of the telos of marriage is.
And she concludes,
not procreation,
but the exclusive and permanent commitment
of the partners to one another
is the essential point and purpose of marriage.
Now, nothing I've said
about this court opinion
is an argument for or against same-sex marriage,
but it is an argument against the claim
that you can favor or oppose same-sex marriage
while remaining neutral
on the underlying moral and religious questions.
So all of this is to suggest
that at least in some
of the hotly contested
debates about justice and rights
that we have in our society,
the attempt to be neutral,
the attempt to say
it's just a matter of consent
and choice and autonomy,
we take no stand,
that doesn't succeed.
Even the court,
which wants to be neutral
on these moral and religious disputes,
finds that it can't.
What then about our second question?
If reasoning about the good
is unavoidable
in debates about justice and rights,
is it possible?
If reasoning about the good
means that you must have
a single principle or rule
or maxim
or criterion
for the good life,
that you simply plug in
every time you have
a disagreement about morality,
then the answer is no.
But having a single principle or rule
is not the only way,
not the best way
of reasoning
either about the good life
or about justice.
Think back,
think back to the arguments
that we've been having here
about justice and about rights
and sometimes about the good life.
How have those arguments proceeded?
They've proceeded
very much in the way
that Aristotle suggests,
moving back and forth
between our judgments about particulars,
particular cases, events, stories, questions,
back and forth between our judgments
about particular cases
and more general principles
that make sense of our reasons
for the positions we take
on the particular cases.
This dialectical way
of doing moral reasoning
goes back to the ancients,
to Plato and Aristotle,
but it doesn't stop with them
because there is a version
of Socratic or dialectical moral reasoning
that is defended
with great clarity and force
by John Rawls.
In giving an account
of his method of justifying
a theory of justice.
You remember,
it's not only the veil of ignorance
and the principles
that Rawls argues for.
It's also a method of moral reasoning,
reasoning about justice,
that he calls reflective equilibrium.
What is the method
of reflective equilibrium?
It's moving back and forth
between our consistent
and consistent judgments
and our consistent judgments.
So, in the case of the law of law,
we consider judgments
about particular cases
and the general principles
we would articulate
to make sense of those judgments.
And not just stopping there,
because we might be wrong
in our initial intuitions.
Not stopping there,
but then sometimes revising
our particular judgments
in the light of the principles
once we work them out.
And in particular cases.
The general point is this,
and here I quote Rawls,
a conception of justice
can't be deduced
from self-evident premises.
It's justification
is a matter of the mutual support
of many considerations,
of everything fitting together
into one coherent view.
And later in a theory of justice,
he writes,
moral philosophy is Socratic.
We may want to change
our present considered judgments
once their regulative principles
are brought to light.
Well, if Rawls accepts that idea
and advances that notion
of reflective equilibrium,
the question we're left with is,
he applies that
to questions of justice.
Not to questions of morality
and the good life.
But, and that's why
he remains committed
to the priority
of the right over the good.
He thinks the method
of reflective equilibrium
can generate shared judgments
about justice and the right,
but he doesn't think
they can generate shared judgments
about the good life,
about what he calls comprehensive
moral and religious questions.
And the reason he thinks that
is that he says that
in modern societies
there is a fact of reasonable
pluralism about the good.
Even conscientious people
who reason well
will find that they disagree
about questions of the good life,
about morality and religion.
And Rawls is likely
right about that.
He's not talking about
the fact of disagreement
in pluralist societies.
He's also suggesting
that there may be persisting,
disagreeing,
disagreements
about the good life
and about moral
and religious questions.
But if that's true,
then is he warranted
in his further claim
that the same can't be said
about justice?
Isn't it also true
not only that we,
as a matter of fact,
disagree about justice
in pluralist societies,
but that at least
some of those disagreements
are reasonable disagreements
in the same way?
Some people favor
a libertarian theory of justice.
Others,
a more egalitarian theory of justice.
And they argue.
And there is pluralism
in our society
as between free market,
laissez-faire,
libertarian theories of justice
and more egalitarian ones.
Is there any reason,
is there any difference
in principle
between the kind
of moral reasoning
and the kind of disagreements
that arise when we debate
about justice
and the meaning of free speech
and the nature
of religious liberty?
Look at the debates we have
over appointees
to the Supreme Court.
These are all disagreements
about justice and rights.
Is there any difference
between the fact
of reasonable pluralism
in the case of justice and rights
and in the case of morality and religion?
In principle,
I don't think that there is.
In both cases,
what we do when we disagree
is we engage with our interlocutor,
as we've been doing here
for an entire semester.
We consider the arguments
that are provoked by particular cases.
We try to develop the reasons
that lead us to go one way
rather than another.
And then we listen
to the reasons of other people.
And sometimes we're persuaded
to revise our view.
Other times we're challenged
at least to shore up
and strengthen our view.
But this is how moral argument proceeds,
with justice,
and so it seems to me also,
with questions of the good life.
Now, there remains a question
of what is the moral argument?
And it's a further worry,
and it's a liberal worry.
What about if we're going to think
of our disagreements
about morality and religion
as bound up with our disagreements
about justice?
How are we ever going to find
our way to a society
that accords respect
to fellow citizens
and to the people we love?
It depends, I think,
on which conception
of respect one accepts.
On the liberal conception,
to respect our fellow citizens'
moral and religious convictions
is, so to speak,
to ignore them
for political purposes,
to rise above or abstract from
or to set aside
those moral and religious convictions,
to leave them undisturbed,
or to carry on our political debate
without reference to them.
But that isn't the only way,
or perhaps even the most plausible way
of understanding the mutual respect
on which democratic life depends.
There is a different conception
of respect,
according to which we respect
our fellow citizens' moral
and religious convictions,
not by ignoring,
but by engaging them,
by attending to them,
sometimes by challenging
and contesting them,
sometimes by listening
and learning from them.
Now, there is no guarantee
that a politics of moral
and religious attention
and engagement
will lead in any given case
to agreement.
There is no guarantee
it will lead even to appreciation
for the moral and religious convictions
of others.
It's always possible,
after all,
that learning more about a religious
or a moral doctrine
will lead us to like it less.
But the respect of deliberation
and engagement
seems to me a more adequate,
more suitable ideal
for a pluralist society,
and to the extent
that our moral and religious disagreements
reflect some ultimate plurality
of human goods,
a politics of moral engagement
will better enable us,
so it seems to me,
to appreciate
the distinctive goods
our different lives express.
When we first came together
some 13 weeks ago,
I spoke of the exhilaration
of political philosophy
and also of its dangers,
about how philosophy works
and has always worked
by estranging us
from the familiar,
by unsettling
our settled assumptions.
And I tried to warn you
that once the familiar turns strange,
once we begin to reflect
on our circumstance,
it's never quite the same again.
I hope you have by now experienced
at least a little of this unease,
because this is the tension
that animates critical reflection
and political improvement,
and maybe even the moral life as well.
And so our argument comes
to an end in a sense,
but in another sense goes on.
Why, we asked at the outset,
why do these arguments keep going
even if they raise questions
that are impossible ever finally to resolve?
The reason,
is that we live some answer
to these questions all the time.
In our public life
and in our personal lives,
philosophy is inescapable
even if it sometimes seems impossible.
We began with the thought of Kant
that skepticism is a resting place
for human reason,
where it can reflect upon
its dogmatic wanderings,
but it is no dwelling place
for permanent settlement.
To allow ourselves simply to acquiesce
in skepticism or in complacence,
Kant wrote,
can never suffice
to overcome the restlessness of reason.
The aim of this course
has been to awaken
the restlessness of reason
and to see where it might lead.
And if we have done at least that,
and if the restlessness
continues to afflict you
in the days and years to come,
then we together have achieved
no small thing.
Thank you.
Funding for this program
Additional funding provided by...